all right hello welcome cohort 8 um
thank you all for sharing your um hellos
in the first minutes so for the rest of
this
meeting briefly we'll cover the meeting
structure for this interval of activity
and a little bit about our Niche and uh
to whatever extent you'll come to
explore it and modify it as well and
then um we'll kind of discuss one foot
in chapter one one foot in any other
general questions because that's kind of
where chapter 1 and 10 are at they're
like book ends they kind of lead in and
lead out so it is a good approach
chapter as behooves of chapter one so
this uh cohort 8 live meeting is our
landing page if you want to bookmark
that one it's a good one um and as
briefly mentioned cohort 7 will be
active at the same time weekly going
through the second half of the book so
you're welcome to join you're welcome to
rewatch videos from any cohort you're
welcome to join live at the same time
slot weekly at which um time alternating
weeks it'll be from the second half of
the book like next week at this time
will'll
be people saying hello in cohort 7 slh
whoever is there and going over chapter
6 and then when we're on chapter 2
they'll be on chapter 7 and so on um and
and the the the day of the meeting a
recording is posted so it's kind of like
the synchronous element and the rhythm
of two weeks per chapter um with uh lots
of edges coming in and out so to briefly
go over this Koda document
um at any time anyone can write a
question in the zoom chat or raise your
hand in Zoom so just any anything that
you want to clarify or or um
just go for it um and uh it this
document has like open comment access
and then also you can request edit
access if for some reason like your
email just hasn't been added to to edit
the the to add directly so um top page
you can right click and download the PDF
of the textbook and it's just a welcome
page directory has some pages linked um
onboarding this this is like some more
information about onboarding to The
Institute overall there's a lot of other
projects and activities outside of the
textbook group so check it out and also
learning practices like we come from
many different backgrounds we have many
different time availabilities many
different um affordances are are
accessible to us we have many different
preferences for where we go and so on so
um
adding different
activities that is like okay when we
time box and um you know C in to be
learning and applying active inference
what is that really looking like and uh
what's what's a a healthy and a
productive blend for us and uh some of
those are solitary some of those are in
your own Knowledge Management
environment some of those might be in
this open source knowledge environment
or in another repository
somewhere um contribute to the textbook
group here again there's more ways to do
than not to do with contributing so if
you feel like yeah I'd love to improve
the synchronous or the asynchronous
components of this group um or or
there's other places to contribute
outside of textbook group too so that
Journey might take you there but it
could be anything
from playing at some point like a live
role in the meetings for example the
later time slot uh is going to be
facilitated by Andrew Pasa who has
joined textbook group also so many times
and and will will pitch fast balls also
and facilitate those discussions um
taking notes and and
describing developing different code
examples um asking questions this is
going to be like a totally vital element
like a lot of times it can feel like
what we don't understand is you know our
limitation or something but actually
when we externalize that question
we can make a lot of interesting
learnings and progress together so check
out different ways to contribute if that
is exciting the meetings page has the
past completed cohorts and the two
ongoing cohorts so that's kind of like
the like organizational about the
textbook group and you can fold pages
and Koda like that and also you can make
it light or
dark if if it looks different on your
screen but I'm using the dark
version all right then there's two other
main sections there's the textbook and
then there's kind of our discourse so
first the textbook
itself we
have the pages in a table and you can
download these tables or you know make
but these it may become relevant and
also Koda is really cool can make your
own Koda or you can play around but by
putting at you can tag any page or
person or even row so like at page one a
mouse over shows that or at
surprise is going to be a link to the
active inference
ontology or different other places where
it's been
mentioned thank you for posting Nick
awesome
so that's the Page by Page and also you
can click on someone's uh
token icon and you'll jump to their
location in Kota so if you click on the
4D you'll you'll jump to where I am um
so it's just Page by Page okay uh then
we get to the chapters so there's 10
chapters and three
appendices um there's detailed table of
contents just skimming and just
familiarizing and many Coates of paint
will just come up again and again with
just like kind of taking a deep breath
and just reading it and just you know
there's stuff that's erroneous that
we've discovered there's stuff that is
ambiguous or or over under precise or
just there's there's so many different
readings but just sticking with it on a
first read and staying in the game
you'll be reducing your uncertainty then
there's the sections here so this is
kind of where we go when we're going to
have like the chapter one discussion and
there's there's there's a few main each
of these chapter Pages have a few main
components first there's a um kind of
like a 20 minutu is overview that Oli
and I did over several days these are um
you know they're fun
um and we just sort of contextualize
like what is this chapter doing in the
context of the book and just what are
the what are the sections of the chapter
basically then there's these questions
that are all part of this underlying
questions table which we're going to get
back to but you can upvote questions
that you think are
interesting and we'll kind of always
prioritize or
frontload written questions that people
have added in and then when um and then
live questions that people have that
will enter into arose and then you know
failing that we kind of just return to
highly interesting questions and then
this canvas has some questions are
answerable debatable others are more
just
discurs so you can always check out that
canvas and read and add
more you know no need to delete anything
per se um but add more and and um so it
goes so that's like the questions
section of each page and then at the
bottom there's uh
sometimes short sometimes
vast a little bit more
unstructured so usually when we're
having a
discussion there if it's like kind of
outside of the um realm of a question
per se sometimes we're just like or just
it's like a question but we just are
doing out in the open it's not a fully
formed question yet um we we will um put
it there so it's like everything's in a
state of Open Source and contributive
enjoyment and you know does active
inference currently allow for learning a
model structure it's like it does but
that's not reflected here but if you see
that and you go yeah and I'm curious
about this then you know add it there or
you can select
text and add a
comment or you could add a link that's
relevant and so everything is just if
you see some discrepancy between like
what you'd want that page to be and what
it is in your
observation you can change your mind or
you can change the page basically as we
will come to see so that's how the
chapters are overview
video questions and disc course for
everybody's um addition and and uh
reading and then some more scattered
topics over the years that people have
discussed so that's the
chapters then there's figures so here
it's like screenshots and just the
figure names and this comes up all the
time because we'll tag like at figure
1.1 and then you can get a mouse over
and you can see these figures and and
these are also helpful just to to see
and to kind of Be Inspired technically
or to to make some artistic rendering of
or all
this um the equations section so here
are screenshots similarly of the
taggable equations like you can just say
like equation
2.1 then um for those who want to
explore a little bit of latch and and uh
using Ai and so on here's latch re
renderings of the equations and in this
latch column is the plain text
latch so if you want to you can utilize
those and then using just the simple
Koda generative AI from the latek here's
like explanation summary code where is
it important what are the variables now
these are just sort of a little bit like
a low context
Generation Um about what what are some
related but but their conversation
starters for sure to just go from the
latch of Base
equation these are some you know and
then do you have it you know would you
phrase one differently would you add one
would you remove one it's not relevant
like that's already you're in the sort
of metacognitive and learning and
relevance realization process by
exploring it that way whatever your
level of math familiarity is
okay thank you Marvin I'll will return
to that um boxes and tables these are
just similar for the equations and
figures they're just for the boxes and
the tables so that's just this section
is just the um kind of parsing of the
textbook itself I'm just going to return
briefly to to that um important piece I
didn't uh mention so this is like when
everybody registered they gave a a self
assess 0 to 100 on four questions which
is how familiar are you with active
inference and then also how familiar are
you with Computer Science Biology and
math which are kind of like three of the
disciplinary areas that these
conversations are are related to so the
xois is familiarity with active
inference so for example person who put
100 let's just say um they also rated
themsel as 78 or whatever in biology
and 100 in
math so what this is
showing there's a few interesting
patterns here first intering pattern is
there's a sharp psychological drop off
of
people at
80 very few people rate themselves as
familiar with active Ence above 80 again
this doesn't even this is all self
assessed so so um you you could um you
could
even you know smile and chuckle at some
of these
but there's and then there's and then it
doesn't show the density but there's a
strong at 50 like maximal uncertainty
and then like other than that what this
shows is we run the self assessed and
probably externally assessed gamut from
those with little familiarity with math
computer science and biology and
Neuroscience to very very high expertise
in those areas
so that's just kind of the situation and
the fun is we we can't necessarily
presuppose that any given um technique
or topic is going to be familiar to
others like just we have we're we're
we're living in different places in the
world and we have different educational
backgrounds and all of that but this
kind of
just in one visualization shows that a
little bit with a like almost
complete pain
painting of how familiar we are with
these different
topics okay and then just this last um
main section discourse so here's a lot
of the things that people have added
over the years so again questions are a
key aspect and you can add questions by
by um going to the bottom of some
uh
subsection like here we're in chapter
one and you just can go to the bottom I
can you can make a button too to add it
and then just hitting enter
there and then you're adding a question
and that will show up in the chapter one
filtered view so or or there's you know
so there's ways to add questions um
applying active
inference this one is is going to come
come up again and again I mean learning
and applying active inference is kind of
the bigger picture that's what we do at
The Institute so if that is your
interest um you also may want to check
out like there's there's many many links
and we can return to this more
specifically we're not going to jump in
at this minute to just where are all the
applications hosted and all that but
they're out there um and there's more to
make um math learning group is kind of
like a special subgroup um that has done
different things over the
seasons last uh cohort activity uh Dr
Octopus was leading like a group and so
there's some sessions with octopus and
and he did a lot of other work too
there's math learning resources so these
are some background information but like
everyone's going to be in a different
place and this is going to trickle out
into learning like probability and
stochastic systems dynamical systems
linear algebra all these different
topics that are explored a little bit in
the appendix they're just kind of noted
um and also nowadays using chat-based
generative AI is an excellent way to
learn and go back to those um
foundations um also the SPM textbook is
a great place to go for understanding
friston at all's trajectory into active
inference um notation we can return to
again later with equations and stuff
there's a lot there math learning
questions these are kind of like meta
questions about math
learning um math
overviews some um people have written
and contributed just to to more uh just
to breakdowns of the chapters about
certain math things so but again this
just shows like there's there's people
who want to um you know for whom it will
be the first time seeing a basian
equation or for whom linear regression
or matrix multiplication may be
unfamiliar and then also there are those
who want to really explore the the
analytical rigor and understand bayy
mechanics and all these other topics at
a really advanced level and uh you're
either if if you leave a trace you're
either going to be contributing to
important educational materials that
will help others immensely Andor
contributing to Frontier research so go
for it um projects this is a table where
people can like list kind of concepts
for projects some of these are actually
did very much continue on more broadly
the activities page activities. active
inference do Institute will link you to
like ongoing projects at The Institute
other things that are hosted here and
then other projects that are happening
in the ecosystem so if you want to just
get involved in projects that have
little to do with the textbook there's a
lot of ways that you can find out about
that and propose your own and then here
is um just like things that people have
ideas people have brought up related to
the textbook group itself um code we
there's we we'll return to it
but yeah SPM textbook that's statistical
parametric
mapping so important little
historical
Trivium
okay um the reason why Carl friston is
the most cited
neuroscientist even sort of outside SL
prior to the free energy principle and
active inference development thrust of
the last like 19 is years is this
statistical toolbox for processing
neuroimaging data like fmri and EEG so
the textbook and the documentation the
textbooks last hard cover publication
was 2007 and then since then there's
documentation online and there's also
like a recent 2025 release of the
software package it's in mat lab some of
the methods are written in it we we may
or may not explore those this is really
really good for showing in a well-worked
and well-studied system of Interest like
how do you go from the data that comes
off of the fmri machine on through the
kinds of smoothing and statistical
assessments that lead to your ability to
do like dynamic causal modeling and
counterfactuals on base graphs and
understanding and modeling cognitive
behavioral systems so it's um kind of
the the precursor to active inference
but it it also really helps ground it in
experimental
paradigms um then T in terms of frisen
all trajectory into active inference um
I mean in terms of their historical
development of studying perception and
action systems empirically
leading into the generalizations that
are seen in active inference and free
energy principle but also in terms of
one of Us's individual learning
trajectories because the SPM
documentation textbook is a really good
um if
dense review of parametric basian and
non-parametric statistics in a specific
empirical Paradigm so that can really
help ground a lot of the discussions of
like statistics and probability that
come up um code here's a table that um
links to other documents but here's
several dozen in different computer
languages and there's other ones that
that aren't added but I mean this is
again like a classic collaborative
annotation task it's like adding these
different examples building them in
different languages so especially in mat
lab Python and Julia but there's also
some other stuff in in go and some other
things we can discuss um ideas and
insights if it's not a question but
somebody just wants to like be like yeah
wow that was kind of like a really
insightful conclusion of this part of
the book or here's what this made me
realize um resources here uh is great
place to post resources Ali created this
table um with a nice
sorting from less technical to more
technical so this is another Learning
Journey to explore
videos of course you can check our
Channel I think earlier somebody
mentioned machine learning Street talk
and there's other channels that
variously make um relevant material um
and but also like throughout the
discourse there's a lot of resources
posted future textbook groups there's a
um Anonymous feedback form there's also
like many other many many many
discussions about um ranging from um
hopeful and as irational to
frustrated uh about you know how do we
learn and apply active inference in in
this time from different backgrounds and
with the tools that we have so if that's
an interesting question to you there's a
lot of food for thought here erata has
several identified like typos or small
errors some of them have been like
subtly updated in um kind of sub
versions in the um at the MIT press
website uh others we we have sent and
they may be included like just in a
future kind of typo fixing edit of the
textbook um so that's just some random
stuff and then last section just acting
tables again we'll dig more into these
more topically as they come up but
there's the active inference onology
this is kind of like our language
agnostic dialect it's that we use to
interface between different natural
languages and some of the technical and
analytical formalisms that are used in
active
inference there's um this is from an
earlier literature meta analysis project
that some people may want to um pick
back up just several hundred papers you
could also just do literature searches
and things like that and then also
there's the um table of several hundred
videos that have been produced from
different
series um so scanning through the
papers and the um titles of guest
streams even without viewing the videos
can help you just get a good first pass
on what the discourse is up to what are
some key topics and you could search for
not that the title will find everything
but you know you may just s oh
organizations or something like that and
then you might find some relevant
uh title but then also those words and
there's the journal for searching more
densely so that's kind of our
um
space the synchronous meetings of course
are awesome and fun and we get to see
each other and have emergent discussion
and
everything and um also there's the time
between the meetings when we engage in
the learning practices you can add your
information if you if you're okay with
it being public because it is um you can
add information to this table you can
message and connect with people um in in
the zoom chat but in terms of the Rhythm
and just to kind of close this section
we basically meet at these times in this
link where we are right now and we try
to keep one foot connected to the focal
topic or it's sort of our strange
attractor
so starting with a quote or kind of
stapling it to a concept that's
mentioned in the text on a specific page
is a great way to to begin um you know
General lifelong floating uncertainties
and and
wonderings also can be welcome um it
helps us have a convergence and uh
relevant Focus
to just be like okay we're in Chapter 2
you know where's a quote and then
connect that and uh there's no end to
the amount of pre-play you can do with
preparing extensive
questions and so on so of course we
can't and won't linearly fit every
single uncertainty and everything we
have into these one hour meetings but uh
between people learning and Publishing
on their own blogs and repos and linking
in week by week and reviewing what
questions people have have thoughtfully
prepared and bring to the
table
like it it seems far away in one sense
to look at May 2025 but we can also
learn a ton over these coming
months
so any like logistical or Niche
questions otherwise we will go to
chapter one and just
like pick up with any page or quote or
question that anyone has could you just
give me an overview of the mission of
The Institute that you are leading yeah
to make active inference accessible and
applicable and just and you're just a
nonprofit doing that or what's your
connection to other organizations we're
uh
Standalone volunteer nonprofit We have
relationships with some other um
Partners do you do you have any
connections to the Santa Fe
Institute not
organizationally
okay but if they want to they can send
emails and I know that they're exploring
that and and there's there's there's
diffusion of peoples and ideas which is
all awesome but and you know whatever
streamlined and useful let's um see what
happens
okay um sorry I have a very concrete
question uh like H how how will this uh
work moving forward um between meetings
we each read like the chapter and
prepare as much as we want and then do
we step through the chapter during the
meeting or like how how will How would
how would it look structurally these
meetings good question like you could
review previous recordings but in the
end it's like who's there in the moment
and then there's going to be some blend
between um someone who's like um you
know this is what my dissertation
research is about and here's how I
prepared these few things and I see
these three paths but I'm not sure what
you know it's like someone might have
prepared a ton other people will just be
like okay I I did look at it or I didn't
look at chapter but I'm just here to see
what's up and then um usually when it's
just outside of this onboarding type
session um it's basically as will go now
it's like I'll open up okay we're on
chapter one we can did anyone so did
anyone add a written question like is
there any question that somebody here
added that we that's likely going to be
down on the bottom that we can look at
or or is there some other question that
somebody here wants to look at
regardless of whether it was written
prior um or is there some
specific quote or figure or
equation so it's like for who's here is
there a question or a section of the
book that is um exciting for them that
that that they want to go
into um and and then if if again to
toally failing that we can just pick a
random question that either does or
doesn't have discourse or just like okay
Chance favors the prepared mind like
what does this mean to us in the context
of active
inference um okay Nick is each chapter
spread out over the two live meetings
yeah each um each
chapter occurs for two weeks but again
it's like next week it'll be in that in
you know seven or however many eight
hours later so if you want to join then
discuss chapter one again great if you
want to join next week at 15 UTC it'll
be discussing chapter 6 that would also
be welcome but then in two weeks it'll
be at this time with chapter
two Sylvia I can't add a question to the
table does it require edit access yeah
it does require edit access just request
access and I'll I'll add it when I'm
just logged in differently but this new
row button at the bottom if you have
edit access you can just add a new row
and
just no
question oh yeah huh how do we access
that panel when we're not in a zoom
meeting where's the link for this um so
I'm just going to put this is the cohort
like this page is the one I'm looking at
now you can open that in your browser
anytime okay and then you'll you'll
request edit access if you don't have it
but everybody has comment access even
like when they're not logged in um and
then from there you just like chapter
one that's a hyperlink to go to this
chapter one page or you can navigate in
the
sidebar okay and then the the discourse
is in this panel and you know
just add
add if you think it's cool um but yeah
well just so you know over the next week
or two people will get their their
footings request edit access and I'll um
provide
it and then um yeah like everyone
reading this will have
questions the the questions will will
run the gamut from like X ential
philosophical to just like
syntactic and semantic like what does
surprise mean here and all of those
spectrum of questions are really
useful and identifying your uncertainty
and then pursuing it from there is a
huge way to learn and the more specific
that that uncertainty comes to be like
how did they get from equation this to
that or why is this arrow in this figure
like that or does it have to be then
you'll come to some satisfaction and
then you'll see exactly how you're
learning and reducing your uncertainty
through action whereas you know not
writing it down or closing the book then
you're not going to reduce that
uncertainty you're just going to not pay
attention to
it but yeah what's a what's a related to
chapter one or just in
overview what are what
are things people are are like thinking
about or
wondering I could have a go a
question
um on um on page nine on the in the
first bullet point on page nine
um it's talking about action and
perception but then it's also saying
learning is yet another way to minimize
free energy however it is not
fundamentally different from
perception it simply operates at a
slower time scale so I guess my question
I have like no Neuroscience biology
background like is there is there kind
of an
obvious sort of Intuition or something
differentiating learning with perception
and
why why they operate on different time
scales I'd like to build on that
question somebody gave me an interesting
definition of
persuasion where they claimed persuasion
is just a different form of
learning yeah belief update in and uh
you know if someone says well the you
know Carbon has a mass of 12 units and
somebody's like they don't know you know
they have a broad prior belief and then
that updates it or whether they're being
persuaded that it's 12 like that's some
kind of
contextual what I I could add more
thought or what does anyone think about
how learn learning and perception are
related I could say um for me uh for me
the key Insight of active inference is
that when an organism relates with the
environment there's this Freedom between
two options that you can update the
environment or you can update your
beliefs whichever is easier and so free
energy minimization uh determines which
is going to be easier but so perception
would be updating your beliefs in the
way that learning is updating your
beliefs it's just that perception is
maybe one way to think about is maybe
the time scale is different but another
way is just the the apparatus is
different but that's but they're both
about updating beliefs as opposed to
updating the
environment thank you Andreas yeah like
let's just say a ball is moving across
our visual
fields we could think of it as
perception of the ball moving across the
field or we could think about as
learning and belief updating of the ball
moving across the field and so learning
is sometimes used to refer to slower
updating
processes um in a neural network like
artificial neural network um perception
might refer to just the the single pass
forward inference whereas learning would
be more about the weight
updating and then even slower kinds of
like structural learning could happen
when the structure of the graph is
changing but again like a ball moving
even that is more generically described
as belief updating and then whether we
associate that with the phenomenology of
perception and like that that it entails
a perceiver and all of that or whether
we think of that as doing learning on
the position of the ball but then we
might say like well um learning would be
something that's more generic or slower
time scale than perception
like if we're learning the um
gravitational constants we say well we
perceived a bunch of balls flying across
the visual field and then we did
learning on some variable like what is
the gravitational constants but
considered from those two sides of the
coin the two ways to uh reduce free
energy change the mind which could be
change perceptual like beliefs or change
more cognitive beliefs which is
associated more with learning but
they're all part of the belief updating
structure as opposed to reducing free
energy through action but both yeah I
just want to build on and ask a a
question about discontinuous learning
think of that in terms of Paradigm
shifts or phase transitions in your
belief system you know there there
become moments where you know you have
maybe a dramatic Insight Aha and it
completely turns your mind in a New
Direction so that's a different kind of
learning than just sort of this
continuous ball in the air I'm more
interested in the in the Paradigm Shift
kind of
learning is when you watch a movie for
example there is learning that you get
in every scene about a character about
what's really going on but every now and
then you get a real turn in the movie a
real pivot in the movie where it shifts
your mind in a totally new Direction and
it's the phase transitions that really
really I think
uh change the search function for the
engine I guess because it now looks a
little bit more like a a random walk or
something
yeah I mean whether that is um belief
updating in a discrete belief space
which is discontinuous whether it's a
extremely rapid continuous update that
when viewed out looks like a step
function whether it's structure learning
there's a lot of ways to to Nuance that
and even to connect it to Paradigm
shifting and and discontinuous change
like that um Andreas and then
montin yeah so the alternative to
perceptional learning would be like to
destroy the ball or hide the ball or
stop the motion of the ball or ignore
the ball like there's all these other
ways that would be neither perception
nor learning I just want to add that
yes um what I he about is this
conceptual changes and I was thinking
about uh what is the exact difference
between an insight and recognition also
just phenomenologically wise and I was
really thinking about uh what this
difference is related on on what level
in the hierarchy uh this belief is
changing so very deep beliefs up in the
hierarchy those are more considered
parad time shifts and those lower in the
hierarchy if those beliefs are getting
in there those are just recognitions and
just becoming aware of the perceptual
environment and I was thinking about how
you guys reflect on this yeah because
the uh if you go to the lower levels I
mean an echo chamber in social media is
a kind of Paradigm that it just operates
at a totally different speed than
Paradigm shifts in science but if you go
to Echo chamber you actually have the if
correct the higher level beliefs stay
constant for the just only reinforcement
so there's no inside transfer on higher
level well they if you go back to Thomas
Coon's definition of what a paradigm is
it defines it defines the questions
you're allowed to ask under that
particular
Paradigm and one of the one of the
points he makes about paradigms is
there's no last Paradigm you know it's
it's like a fractal it's all the way
down you never it's Rush dolls you never
actually get to the end of the paradigms
and and and you isolate yourself this is
a new theory in AI into AI
neighborhoods depending on the Paradigm
you're operating with and that's got
very different consequences in terms of
like the world will continue to separate
into different belief systems regardless
of where AI goes it will be a continuous
part of of of how intelligence
evolves okay it seems that Paradigm
shifts for me is different understanding
but perhaps resolvement will become
later just say I come to I've come to
the same conclusion myself particularly
relating to uh to you know
religious uh
events they are you know spiritual
shifts major changes in perception they
are the same thing as a messing with a
belief at a high at a particularly deep
level of one's predictive you can't help
you have to rewrite the whole story all
the way up right and you experience
everything very different and I've had a
few of those religious experiences which
is why the question is kind of
fundamental to me I've had a total
re looking in a totally new Direction
than I than I was looking before as a
result of like a single very brief
experience it's a phase transition from
water to ice basically it's it's it's a
radically different shaping of
perceptions yeah and what this model
does is it gives us a very clear way in
which I would argue no no religion yet
has in terms of how to bring that about
how to trigger
it well
true but I'm back to the point is like
there there is no such thing as the
perfect Paradigm I mean even even
believed that the old generation of
scientists had to die off before you
could actually get to a new paradigm
because they it was too too hard to
change it at the very end it's like the
religious transition that St Augustine
went through that kind of thing yeah so
um Ali and then Andreas anyone else with
their handr but yeah
interesting yeah I just wanted to point
out uh Michael Levan's recent uh article
self-improving memory about um how
learning or actually memory formation
um occurs even uh in very basic uh
complex agents such as uh molecular uh
biological um uh I mean complex systems
uh so basically uh the point here is
that uh when when an agent learns about
its environment it's not so much about
uh the Fidelity or uh the exact modeling
of of its environment but more uh the
Salient parameters of the environment uh
in which it tries to um preserve so uh
the higher it goes in its hierarchical
structure of its memory formation uh the
more uh the more it needs to keep those
Salient parameters or as John Veri would
call uh the more it needs to uh realize
the um to do the uh relevance
realization that's the term uses uh so
basically uh the thing about perception
and learning and why uh they are closely
interrelated uh I think depends uh in
part uh on this process of memory
formation uh I mean uh the
higher I mean um the higher we go up
onto uh on the latter of this um
hierarchy
iCal um generative modeling of of the
environment uh the more it needs to
retain uh the relevant and uh Salient
parameters of the environment so on the
very basic levels uh some of some of the
uh perceived elements would not be
needed uh for uh long-term perseverance
of that agent through the environment
but uh um as we know the
longer the agent wants to persevere
through the environment uh the more it
needs to attend to those uh Salient and
relevant uh parameters and one other
thing I wanted to point out relating to
this um interconnection between
perception and action uh Alan Barto has
a a famous code relating these two um
parameters as saying uh which I think is
beautiful uh he says perception is
simulated action uh which will come to
in chapter two why it can be also
applied uh for active inference so uh
yeah we can look at perception and
action uh in a dual form from two uh
complementary um viewpoints but at the
end of the day they both somehow provide
uh this the same formal uh structure
looking whether we look at the
environment or from the
environment um to um from the agent to
the environment or from the environment
to the agent when you say perception is
simulated action isn't that
imagination not exactly you see uh when
well it comes to as it plays on uh the
elements of ecological Psych ology you
see and the concept of affordances from
the ecological psychology but of course
affordances are used in a very different
sense in active inference but um in
brief when uh an agent sees an
affordance an opportunity to act upon it
doesn't perceive that object or that
element of the environment just as a
thing but it sees as it it SE the
element as an opportunity to and how the
agent can act upon that opportunity
right how does that how is that
different from imagination
though uh
well I'm not sure if I understood your
question correctly but uh to my mind
when we talk about imagination we don't
necessarily use this kind of affordance
thinking we don't map affordances onto
the object of the environment as a very
simple example when yeah if I see a gun
in a movie in a drawer it's an old
Hollywood thing is like you know
somewhere later in the movie the gun's
gonna get used right so affordance of
the
gun is like the imagination starts
looking ahead as like how is that gun
gonna be used in the story in the
narrative right yeah sure so as it may
be just semantics imagination and you
know and I'm trying to what I'm actually
poking at is is there a real difference
between
imagination or just making predictions
about what I could do H you know under
under inference Theory that's Allis you
see imagination plays um very
significant role in shaping uh the
prediction and uh even our generative
model of the world but uh you see uh as
a as a very simple example when we look
at um um coffee M uh whether we want to
uh I don't know uh hold on to that copy
coffee M uh from uh from the rim or uh I
don't know hold it
in I mean um in an other way uh those
two different perceptions would provide
um a those two different ways of acting
upon that coffee M would provide two
different perceptions of that same
object that's
um it's it's it's a random thought but
I'm building on what you're saying
I'm not criticizing it it makes me think
of like that's how topology works on
mathematics what are the you know what
are and so it's so there's a topological
component of perception I
suspect that yeah that will also return
also just a general comment
like crashing English words or other
natural words into each other it's like
continent scale discussion how is
Imagination related to surprise or you
know it how is a for it's just like they
they have so it's such a broad scope
that it's like it's absurd so it's great
and it's like but it's the it's the it's
the most symbolized coar grain token
that we can share and reference so it's
just like pointing it's like yeah you
know um the North Pole is that way and
so that is is like just a doorway and
then there's the whole generative
modeling process and then when you get
down to it you have um analytical
expressions and specific structured
models that describe like well here's
how I'm thinking about imagination in
this setting this is the cognitive
phenomena that I'm associating with
imagination and that is let me can can I
bring it back to something a little more
data specific then because you I agree
with you when you take the simple words
you get the big Ideas when you take the
big words you the little ideas I think
that's the way I think of words H but
are you familiar with the with the
remembrance bump or the memory bump it's
the point that memories in human
lifespan are not evenly distributed but
but they're actually concentrated
between the years of 15 and 25 or 30 and
the reason for that is because that's
when you are going through the phase
transition of the concept of self that
you had that your parents imposed on you
up until you became a teenager and then
you're Reinventing yourself your adult
sense of self and separating from the
childhood sense of self so it speaks to
a phase transition in a self-referential
way to the concept of self not just the
environment and I'm curious about as you
know because I've got teenage grandkids
as they're going through this biological
process of basically creating their
adult sense of self and separating from
the parents idea of who they should be
uh and there's a lot of data behind that
and so on you can use it to build
predictive models actually of like what
that's why Hollywood does remakes of
movies and stuff like that take the same
story and update it with new generation
and and stuff like that so when you
introduce the self- referential
component to the concept of self not
just the environment how I'm going to be
curious to see how active inference
deals with that self-referential
component yeah keep sketching it out and
seeing what simpler generative model
motifs you can bring in and you'll be
well well well on the way towards that
um Marvin and then Andreas with the
hands rais and then anyone else and then
that will be it I wanted to I've raised
my hand sorry go ahead go
ahead yeah um going back to the
hierarchy uh for me um I'm interested in
looking at that through the middle and I
think what what I'd like to do with
active inference is to say
hey High going up there could could be a
hierarchy going down but I think there's
an essential gap between um the two
minds let's say theing mind so thinking
of an environment saying oh well what is
the unconscious that's presenting
this and is all these answers and then
uh what is this mind that doesn't know
but is able to ask questions and uh you
know engage and investigate and so those
would be like somewhere in the middle of
the hierarchy and that way you can go
further out into the world you can go
off into
abstractions but um you don't have to
worry about them so much because the
main focus is on how these very two very
different ways of looking at things in
terms of what we know and what we don't
know how they match up that's what I'm
interested
to okay thank you um Marvin and then any
final raised hands then that will be
it okay uh quite basic I I'm I'm serous
maybe just I know might be a deep topic
but just basically like what's the
relation what does active inference
imply the predictive processing theory
of the mind or predictive coding because
what I really liked in the preface uh it
says uh we're not simply trying to make
sense of our s Sensations we are
actively creating our sensorium so to me
that sounded a lot like predictive uh
processing or
generative whatever you want to call it
so so so is is predictive processing
just derivation of active inference or
an implication or is it yeah in parallel
yeah great question um I I know that
there's some question in one of the the
chapters but um active predictive
processing so considering the active
prior meeting the observation like on
the retina and including the capacity
for the retina to move active predictive
processing gets you it it it is active
inference they basically are are are
more isomorphic than not in live stream
43 um Maria does an awesome historical
review like going back several thousand
years to this concept of like the active
predictive
elements
[Music]
um they're more similar than not if
you're talking about descending
predictions ascending sensory
information and then the descending
predictions not just being well what
will I
but what will I
do you basically have the scheme for
octave
inference and then there's some slight
differences just um like more like
historically culturally with like well
predictive processing is often discussed
in terms of a hierarchical model but
active influence models they don't have
to be hierarchical models they could
just be single layer but that but
predictive processing arising from like
the
visual
Mamon
Neuroscience so then that's why that
architecture became kind of generalized
from visual perception versus just being
in its most generic system independent
form thank you thank you yeah okay
Martin and then that will be it yes is a
small question I think a small question
uh to state but I think a very
interesting question to think about and
that is the relation between how to view
willpower through the sense through the
lens of active inference and my only gut
feeling is that it has if there is
certain way to look at it interpret it
it would be in how you are able to
resist uh prediction error like how a
how much you are able to um have like
this tension in the model of expected
things and not the expected prediction
uh percent I mean but that's a very
interesting question I I'd like to yeah
think about
cool yeah and just just the predictive
processing predictive coding basian
brain that they they again they all are
are closer than not but there's a few
specific resources if you really want to
split the
hair okay last comment Andrew and then
that will it yeah so on the will I think
that's very much where I'm headed is I
believe there's three Minds there's one
that has these answers there's one that
has these questions one that
investigates and so it's the
investigating mind that kind of pairs
them up and sees oh uh do I want to lean
on perception updating beliefs or do I
want to lean on action updating the
environment if now you could say it's
just a free energy principle but the
theory maybe allows for something more
that there's a third mind that kind of
actively uh applies that to equate those
two but also to decide I'm G to use one
you know I'm gonna lean this way I'm G
to lean that way so then that would be
very willful that's what I'm interested
model the the's book The will the world
is Will and representation or the world
is Will and idea is probably a an
interesting mapping
onto active inference Theory
cool thank you all um hopefully this is
a little taste um of uh lineer
conversation and like I can see that you
all have
many Avenues this makes you explore and
I really encourage you to write them out
so that they're simultaneous and then
contribute them into our Niche where
they're much more digestible than trying
to linearly convey these ideas if you
have them pre-loaded and you're thinking
about it and you're wondering about like
do that Chain of Thought and then we'll
have something to really digest
deliberately over hours and something
that people can add to um rather than
just follow up on so hence the sort of
um live but mainly I mean we're you know
next several hundred hours how do we do
that again remind me just really quickly
the whole doc everything we looked at
with a document is editable so you can
ask and add questions like by adding a
row that was shown um but you can add to
the discourses the canvas that was next
to the question on the row okay
or or or you can just you know write it
on your own blog or make a GitHub repo
and share that link if if if you don't
see the right Nook or cranny in our
shared Niche just write it and then link
it in okay so all right thank you see
you all in um one or two weeks all right
bye